Finding Aid for Charles Henry Sawyer papers, 1930-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Henry Sawyer papers 1930-1997
Sawyer, Charles Henry, 1906-2005
89146 Aa2
Director of the University of Michigan Museum of Art, professor of art and art history. Subject files relating to his University of Michigan activities and to his involvement with various art museums and art associations; and photographs.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles H. Sawyer (Donor No. 6366 ) donated this collection in several accessions beginning in 1985.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research with the exception of a search committee file.
Charles Henry Sawyer was born in Andover, Massachusetts on October 20, 1906, the son of James Cowan and Mary Pepperell Frost Sawyer. In 1929 he earned his Bachelor of Arts from Yale University. He then attended Harvard Law School (1929-1930) and the Harvard School of Fine Arts (1930-1932).
From 1930 to 1940, Sawyer was the curator of the Addison Gallery of American Art at the Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts. He was also an art instructor and chairman of the Art Department at Phillips Academy. In 1934, Sawyer married Katherine ("Kitty") Clay (1908-1998).
Sawyer was the director of the Worcester Art Museum in Worcester, Massachusetts from 1940 to 1947. He was also associated with the Worcester Museum School and served as an adjunct professor of fine arts at Clark University in Worcester.
During World War II, Sawyer served in the US Army's Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Division (1943-1945). He also worked in the Office of Strategic Services' Section on German Art Looting (Fall 1944) and as Assistant Secretary on the Roberts Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in War Areas (June 1945-February 1946).
From 1947 to 1956, Sawyer was dean of the School of Fine Arts (subsequently renamed the School of Architecture and Design) and director of the Division of the Arts at Yale University. He was also professor of history of art, and, from 1947 to 1953, master of Timothy Dwight College at Yale. During those years he received honorary degrees from Amherst College (LHD, 1950), Clark University (LHD, 1953), and the University of New Hampshire (DFA, 1952).
Sawyer left Yale in 1957 to become director of the University of Michigan Museum of Art and professor of art and art history. In 1963, Sawyer founded the Museum Practice Program, a Rackham School of Graduate Studies program with close ties to the Museum of Art. He retired as director in 1972 and as a professor in 1975.
Throughout his career and into his retirement, Sawyer was involved with many committees, advisory councils, and associations in the field of art. Among the organizations that Sawyer worked with are the American Association of Museums, the Art Institute of Chicago, the Amon Carter Museum of Western Art in Ft. Worth, the Association of Art Museum Directors, the College Art Association, the Committee on Art Education, the Committee on Government and Art, the Committee to Rescue Italian Art, Ford Foundation, the Fogg Museum at Harvard, the Museum Publisher's Association, the National Collection of Fine Arts Commission, the New England Museum Director's Council, and the Notre Dame Advisory Council.
Sawyer independently researched German and Dutch architecture in the United States during the 1980s and into the 1990s. In 1984, he wrote an unpublished book Germanic Communities in Texas: Their Domestic Architecture, 1840-1900.
Sawyer's papers document the range of his professional activities as well as his post-retirement projects. The collection spans the years of 1930, when Sawyer was curator at Phillips Academy, to 1997, almost twenty-five years after his retirement from the University of Michigan. Sawyer's correspondence, speeches, and research compose much of the collection; there are also photographs, course descriptions, and committee meeting minutes.
The collection is arranged into the following series: University of Michigan, Organizational Affiliations, Personal, Germanic Architecture, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Art museums.; Sawyer, Charles Henry, 1906-; University of Michigan. Dept. of History of Art.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Art.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Buildings--Michigan--Frankenmuth.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Frankenmuth.; Churches--Michigan--Frankenmuth.; Dwellings--Michigan--Frankenmuth.; Frankenmuth (Mich.)--Buildings.; Frankenmuth (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Frankenmuth (Mich.)--Churches.; Frankenmuth (Mich.)--Dwellings.; German Americans--Michigan--Frankenmuth.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- University of Michigan 1956-1995
  The University of Michigan series documents Sawyer's tenure with the University of Michigan History of Art program as well as his work on various committees while at the university. Documentation of Sawyer's years as the director of the University of Michigan Museum of Art mostly revolves around his appointment to, and retirement from, that position with only scattered material from the intervening years.
  - Director (Box 1)
  - History of Art Dept.
    - Classes (Box 1)
    - Department (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee (Box 1)
    - Search Committee for an Historian of American Art 1990-1992
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022 ]
  - Museum of Art
    - Appointment as Director and Professor of Art 1956 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and other papers 1956-1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1979-1990 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with School of Art (Box 1)
    - Hilarie Faberman Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Notes to Docents (Box 1)
    - Retirement as Director 1972 (Box 1)
    - Samuel Rosenthal (Box 1)
    - Samuel Rosenthal Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Search Committee for Director 1972 (Box 1)
    - Special Reports to University Administration 1958-1978 (Box 1)
  - Museum Practice Program
    - Alumni Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Class Lists (Box 1)
    - Class Speeches 1968-1990 (Box 1)
    - Marjorie "Cricket" Heath (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Program in American Culture (Box 1)
  - Sawyer Fellowship 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - School of Art
    - Courses
      - Decorative Arts
        - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
        - 1974 (Box 1)
      - History
        - 1961 (Box 1)
        - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
        - 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Review Committee 1982 (Box 1)
  - Scientific Club (Box 1)
  - Visual Arts Proposal 1974 (Box 1)
- Organizational Affiliations
  Sawyer's work with the Smithsonian Art Commission (1954-1983) and the National Collection of Fine Art Commission (renamed the National Museum of American Art in 1980) is well documented in the Organizational Affiliations series. This material makes it possible to trace the growth and development of the two organizations, particularly of the Smithsonian. The Frank Lloyd Wright Archives file includes a document recounting Sawyer's personal experiences with the architect. Similarly, the Yale file includes Sawyer's impressions of architect Louis Kahn, gathered from their meetings about the Yale University Art Gallery addition (1951-1953). One gap in this series is the lack of material about Sawyer's affiliation with Clark University, 1942 to 1947 and 1953.
  - Addison Gallery of American Art, (Phillips Academy) 1933-1954 (Box 1)
    (includes photos)
  - Albers-Josef and Anni Albers Foundation (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Science 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Museums
    - General 1941-1949 (Box 1)
    - Accreditation Commission 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Museums (cont.)
    - Accreditation Visiting Committee
      - General 1971-1973 (Box 1)
      - Chicago Art Institute 1972 (Box 1)
      - Minneapolis Institute of Art 1972 (Box 1)
      - Minnesota Museum of Art 1972 (Box 1)
  - American Humanities Seminars (Box 1)
  - Amherst College (Box 1)
  - Amon Carter Museum of Western Art
    - "American Landscape Painting: The Eastern Artist Looks West," April 3, 1975 (lecture) (Box 1)
    - Museum Business 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago (Box 1)
  - Association of Art Museum Directors (Box 1)
  - Book Club (Box 1)
  - College Art Association: Study of Higher Education in the Visual Arts (Box 1)
  - Committee on Art Education (Box 1)
  - Committee on Government and Art (Box 1)
  - Committee to Rescue Italian Art (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation Study, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Frank Lloyd Wright Archives 1994 (Box 2)
  - Harvard University
    - General 1934-1956, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Committee on the Visual Arts (Box 2)
    - Fogg Museum
      - General 1953-1960 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Minutes (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Committee for the Study of the Visual Arts
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Minutes and Reports (Box 2)
  - Museum Publishers Association Committee (Box 2)
  - Museum Training, "Training and Scholarship Program for Future Museum and Advisors, Curators, and College Art Instructors," 1946 (Box 2)
  - National Collection of Fine Arts Commission 1969-1980, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - National Museum of American Art 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - New England Museum Directors Council (Box 2)
  - Notre Dame Advisory Council (Box 2)
  - Rhode Island School of Design (Box 2)
  - Ringling Museum of Art (Florida) (Box 2)
  - Saltzburg Seminar in American Art (Box 2)
  - Slusser (Jean Paul) Memorial (Box 2)
  - Smith College (Box 2)
  - Smithsonian Art Commission 1954-1970, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - Texas Christian University
    - Art History Program 1972-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Course, Arts in American Life 1973 (Box 3)
    - Green Honors Visiting Professor 1973 (Box 3)
  - Timothy Dwight College 1953 (Box 3)
  - University of Texas 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Williams Museum of Art 1983-1994, 2 folders (Box 3)
    (folder 1 includes photograph)
  - Worcester Art Museum 1940-1947 (Box 4)
  - Worcester, Massachusetts Writings 1941 (Box 4)
  - Yale University
    - Letters of recommendation (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, etc. (Box 4)
    - Louis Kahn 1991-1993 (Box 4)
- Personal
  The Personal series includes information about Sawyer's activities in World War II, including a bound copy of the Report of the American Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in War Areas his work helped compile. Also included are the texts of Sawyer's formal speeches as well as a sample of the notecards he used in delivering more informal talks.
  - Art Instruction in English Public Schools, 1936-1938 (Box 4)
    (correspondence and other papers about this book written by CHS)
  - Articles (Box 4)
  - Biographical 1943-1997 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Honors
    - Amherst College Honorary Degree 1950 (Box 4)
      (includes photograph)
    - "Big Wheels," 1971 (Box 4)
    - Clark University Honorary Degree 1953 (Box 4)
    - Phillips Academy undated (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan
      - Development Council 1963 (Box 4)
      - Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award 1971-1974 (Box 4)
    - University of New Hampshire Honorary Degree 1952 (Box 4)
  - Publications (Box 4)
  - Speeches 1930-1970, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Speech Notecards (Box 4)
  - World War II
    - Miscellaneous 1943-1947, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Report of the American Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in War Areas 1946 (Box 4)
- Germanic Architecture
  Sawyer's post-retirement research and writings comprise the Germanic Architecture series. Included is the final draft of his unpublished book Germanic Communities in Texas: Their Domestic Architecture, 1840-1900.
  - Partial Index 1991 (Box 5)
  - Michigan
    - Holland
      - Notes 1991, undated (Box 5)
    - Zeeland
      - 1981 undated (Box 5)
      - Notes 1983, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1976-1988
    - Germanic Communities in Texas: Their Domestic Architecture 1840-1900, 1984, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - "Germans in Saginaw County," 1981 (Box 5)
    - Paper, "The Germans in the Saginaw Valley," 1980 (Box 5)
      (includes photographs)
    - "Germans in Washtenaw County: Some Comparisons and Reflections on Their Domestic Architecture in the Nineteenth Century," 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - "He Studies German Taste in Architecture," 1979 (Box 5)
    - Introduction to Research Project 1978 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1979-1981 (Box 5)
    - Nineteenth Century Domestic German Architecture, Notes 1976-1978 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  Aspects of Sawyers research on Germanic architecture are also documented in the Photographs series, with photographs of German architecture from throughout the Midwest. Dozens of photographs of Dutch architecture from Holland and Zeeland, Michigan are in this series, many with additional background information about the pictured structures. Various posed and informal photographs are also included in this series.
  - German Architecture
    - Michigan
      - Ann Arbor (West Side) (Box 5)
      - Washtenaw County (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Midwest (Indiana, Ohio, Michigan, and Missouri) (Box 5)
    - Ohio
      - Columbus (Box 5)
      - Eastern Region (Box 5)
      - Germantown (Box 5)
      - Western Region (Box 5)
    - North Carolina (Box 5)
    - Wisconsin (Box 5)
  - Holland/Zeeland, Michigan
    - Brick Houses (Box 5)
    - Frame Houses (Box 5)
    - Italianate Houses (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Holland (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Zeeland (Box 5)
    - One-Story Houses (Box 5)
    - Queen Anne Houses (Box 5)
  - Sawyer, Charles H.
    - Professional (Box 5)
    - Personal (Box 5)
  - Unidentified Houses (Box 5)